Hi, we've got another viewer question.
Thank you very much Phase 303
on X or /Twitter, whichever you want to
call it, who asked the question, "Can I
show him how to actually measure the
phase difference between two sine waves
using a Rigol DHO 800 series
oscilloscope?" We certainly can do that.
It's rather interesting. There's several
ways to do it, so let's take a look at
it. So, you can see here we've got two
sine waves. The yellow is channel one,
blue is channel two here, and you can
see that there is a phase difference
between them. The phase difference is
defined as the difference in degrees. A
360° will be one full cycle. So, the
difference in degrees between the two
waveforms at the same reference
location. So, it could be the zero
crossing point like here, for example,
because our zero point is literally
right there. So, that's our zero
crossing point, or it could be the top
or the bottom, the falling edge, rising
edge. It doesn't have to be a sine wave,
could be a square wave, for example, or
triangle wave, whatever waveform it is.
So, let's take that full cycle there.
So, just by eyeballing this with your
mark one eyeball, you'll go, "Okay,
well, you know, if that's 360°, then
that's about, I don't know, 1/10 of
that, maybe." But anyway, let's get the
exact figure from our generator. I've
got a generator over here. Channel one
is our reference here. It's at 0°
because you have to have a reference
somewhere, but it's all relative, and
I've set it to 33°,
and yeah, it seems to be about, you
know, that 30°ish, but we want to
measure it precisely because we've got
the measurement tool for doing this, an
oscilloscope. So, let's get to it. Now,
there's several ways to do this, either
manually or automatic. Automatic is
going to be the easiest way to do it,
and most modern digital scopes will have
the ability for you to automatically
measure phase difference between
channels. So, what we have to do is we
have to go up into measurements up here
and then
where in vertical measurements it's got
nothing to do with the vertical the
voltage of the measurement. So, we want
to go into horizontal over here and we
want to have a look at the features for
the horizontal and really you know, we
can measure the frequency the period the
rise fall time the width and the duty
cycle and all that sort of stuff. But
there's no relative measurements between
two waveforms over there. So, what we
want to do is we want to go over to
other and aha and here's where we could
do it. It's got four different types of
delay measurements and four different
types of phase measurements here and the
phase measurement is the one that we
want cuz it'll give us a number in
degrees out of the 360 as we said before
over the full cycle. The delay will give
us
essentially the same value but in a
different units of time i.e. seconds
microseconds milliseconds nanoseconds
whatever it is. But usually when you're
talking about phase you're talking about
in degrees. So, what are these four
different measurements? What does R to R
R to F and F to R and F to F mean? Well,
R and F mean rising and falling. So,
it's the rising and falling edge of the
waveforms. So, it just gives you
different options there between
different points on the waveform. So,
whoop
a bit tricky to get rid of that. So,
this is considered a rising edge like
this because it's going upwards. So,
these are both rising edges. So, if we
wanted to measure that difference in
there which is what we do want to happen
do want to measure here then we want
rising edge to rising edge or R to R of
those two waveforms. But if you wanted
the rising edge of this one to the
falling edge of the yellow one then you
could do that as well. but that depends
on the circumstances that you want to
measure. So, let's go back in there and
we'll go into other and we will if the
bloody touchscreen works. There we go.
It's touchy. I'm here all week. So, we
want phase R to R like that and bingo,
it's going to add a measurement over
here on the side. So, you notice that
it's not showing any value over there.
That's because we didn't set it up
properly before we hit it. A source A is
chat So, they're both channel two. So,
we want the source to be channel one and
that to be channel two. So, we add that
there and boom, there's our 33 degrees.
We'll just get rid of the other one we
had before. That's dodgy. We can remove
that and bingo, we've got our automatic
measurement and sure enough, there it
is, 32 33 degrees. It's updating like
crazy, but we can actually expand that
and get statistics in here. And you'll
notice that how many counts it's
actually getting these um average values
over. So, 33.1
degrees. There you go, fantastic. And
you'll notice if I change the time base,
that count will reset like that. There
you go. Or if I change the vertical
scale, for example, it will reset those
statistics there. So, that's easy peasy
lemon squeezy, but Dave, what happens if
your oscilloscope doesn't have this
fancy pantsy new um phase measurement
capability like this? Well, there's ways
to do it manually.
Old school. And just so there's no
confusion over which two points it's
measuring, we can actually go in there
and we can actually turn on the
indicator and that will actually track
uh these particular measurements. So, if
I change it on my function generator,
for example, you'll see it, it'll change
in real time like that.
Beauty. But uh if you want the a proper
average value, you see that the average
value is lagging behind, we'll have to
just reset those uh stats there. And if
you've got a tricky waveform or
something, you can actually go into the
settings here, and you can actually uh
like fiddle around with the uh threshold
uh values here and stuff like that, but
we won't go into that uh for this video.
So, but if you've got a more complex
waveform you're looking to get, and it
can't quite do the automated uh
measurement, then you might have to play
around with uh uh amplitude thresholds.
But basically, you should just be able
to uh have that on auto for, you know,
most general waveforms. And you can even
get fancier by saying, "Oh, okay, I want
to actually do manual measurements into
the zoomed-in uh
version of the waveform and things like
that." But, you know, most of the time
you won't have to do that. Well, that uh
zoom thing might come in handy soon. So,
there's other ways we can do this. We
can go older school, not quite old old
school. We'll show you that at the end.
But, uh the next way you can do this is
with uh cursors. So, you can turn
cursors on, and you can see that we've
got horizontal cursors like this, and
we've got vertical cursors like this.
Well, we don't need to dick around with
the vertical cursors. Now, this
oscilloscope, unfortunately, doesn't
have uh give us the ability to actually
measure a uh a cursor delta, it's
called, the difference between the two
cursors in a uh in actual degrees. So,
we can't get a direct phase reading. So,
we're going to have to work out the time
for the full cycle. So, we're going to
have to go back to measurements over
here, and then we're going to have to go
back into horizontal, and then we're
going to have to do the period here, and
we're going to add a period there. And
because it's a 1 kHz waveform we're
talking about here, it's basically bang
on 1 ms there. But, you need to know
that before you can actually do the
calculations with these cursors. But,
just be aware that some scopes might
have more advanced cursor capabilities.
You might be able to set a reference and
then get a phase difference and
different units and things like that.
So, but this one, you know, it's an
entry-level scope. It's already got
ridiculous amount of measurement
capability built in, but
it's not that good. So, what we want to
do is move these cursors to our
reference point, which we'll just say is
the zero line there cuz you've got to
choose a reference. As I said, doesn't
matter where you do it. So, we can use
the cursors with the touch screen, or we
can actually move them. And at the
moment, they're actually tracking like
that. But, we don't want them to track.
So, we're just going to ignore these
vertical cursors here, and we're going
to move our horizontal
cursors like this. And we could sort of
like guesstimate it down in there like
that. But, we'd like a bit more
resolution. So, there's two methods you
can do to get more vertical resolution.
One is to increase your scale like this.
Okay? So, we can see that
they didn't track there. So, we can see,
okay, that's about the point where it
crosses that zero line. And that one's,
you know, it's it's near enough, good
enough for Australia. There it is about
there. But, because the slope of this
waveform is like
it's a bit how you doing.
When it goes across, it's really hard to
see where it crosses that line. We can
actually increase the vertical
resolution here. We can actually use our
vertical control to increase them like
this. Just go way off like that. And
bingo, we can actually get Look at that.
We can actually now see much better
where it actually crosses that zero
point line. And you can see that we had
it. We had it pretty close. Anyway, if I
hold my tongue at the right angle, get
the cursor set up, I think that's where
it crosses the zero Oh, that one's a bit
off. So, we can even expand that further
and then we can use our horizontal
position to bring it over here and then
bring our cursors even finer like that.
So, you can use your horizontal and your
vertical main controls to get a bit more
resolution out of this sucker. So, there
you go. Right, what value have we got?
So, what we're looking for is the delta
or difference between those two X
cursors. So, that would be delta X
there. That's what that triangle symbol
That's actually the symbol delta. So, 95
microseconds. So, you remember before
how I told you that we needed that
period down here. It's gone. It's
vanished. It's less than one
femtosecond. That's femtosecond, right?
Because it's off the screen. We don't
have the full waveform on there. But,
you just remember from before it was 1
ms. So, now get our confuser out here.
microseconds,
okay, divided by
the 1 ms that we had for the entire
period, okay? And that gives us 0.095,
but we want to get that in degrees. So,
we multiply that by 360°
and that gives us uh 34.2.
I still have it set to 33 on my
generator, so it's not as precise as
we'll get in with that automated
measurement. Maybe I'm slightly off on
my cursor. Yeah, I think we're down in
the resolution
of what we can do with our delta cursor
measurement there. So, it's not going to
be as accurate as our automated
measurement, unfortunately, but you
know, it's going to be close enough.
Good enough for Australia. And now, is
it positive 33° or negative 33°? Well,
our channel two waveform, the blue
waveform, is leading, what's called
leading, the channel one waveform here
because it comes before it. So, it's
leading it and that's why if we have a
look on our generator over here, we can
see that we're positive 33°
and that means I'm setting that for
channel two here. Sorry, it's it's
confusingly yellow, which actually goes
into the blue over here. So, yeah, sorry
about that. So, that's positive 33° on
the channel two signal relative to the
channel one. So, when you say it's
positive, that means it's leading. It
comes first. So, zero and then one
degree and then 10 degrees and 20
degrees and 33° over here. If it was
minus, then it'd be minus. It'd be
lagging the channel one waveform. So,
minus 33 would put it on the other side.
But Dave, I'm running an old school
analog oscilloscope. Couldn't be
bothered getting my analog oscilloscope
output. It doesn't have cursors. Some of
the Some of the good analog
oscilloscopes have cursors, but what
happens if you didn't have a cursor?
Well, you've got that's where your
graticule, these grid lines on your
scope for. Sorry, they're quite hard to
see. Maybe I can turn off my lights. So,
we look at our horizontal time base, 20
microseconds per division, okay? And
then we just count the divisions. So,
it's kind of like just before a smidge
before that vertical graticule there.
So, that's 20
40 60
80. Oh, then you got to fiddle around
with it and yeah, maybe we're about that
95 microseconds that we'll get in
before. So, once again, you know, we're
only going to get, you know, 34°. So, we
could be like a percent out there
compared to our 33° that we'll get in
over here. But so, anyway, that's how
you do a phase measurement on
an oscilloscope. Automated, if your
scope's got that feature, is the best
way to do it. You're just going to get
the most accurate number, and it just
puts it there for you. So, we just go
into our measurements here, and and we
can do I can show you like we can do
rising to rising edge, and then falling
to falling edge. It should make no
difference. They're exactly the same
because the rising and falling edge of
these two waveforms bloody shut down.
But, you'll notice one thing, which is a
trap for young players. Once again, it's
all relative. You'll notice that it's
showing minus 33° because we're getting
the yellow waveform
minus the C2 waveform. So, it's giving
us a minus value there. So, we would if
you wanted that to be positive to match
So, you'd have to swap if you want that
the other way around, you'd have to
choose channel two as your source A and
channel one as your source B, and then
rising edge to rising edge and falling
edge to falling edge, and bingo, it's
now positive. So, that's a trap for
young players. You have to keep your
brain engaged when you're actually doing
these measurements to make sure you
actually get the sign correct. You have
to know which one is relative and which
one is leading and lagging, etc. So,
yeah, little trap for young players
there. So, another way to use the
graticule system without actually having
to like count them is
to use single shot sampling. So, let's
let's go vertical again on these so that
we get a nice vertical resolution on
there. Let's go out like this, and we've
got our trigger point right in smack in
the middle there, and our horizontal so
we actually can reset those. So, we
reset our horizontal position. Like, we
can move our position like that, but we
want to reset it, and then we want to
reset our trigger level smack in the
middle like that. No worries. And then
you can actually move your cursor
position, and you'll notice that we're
getting the figure up there that
where we've moved it from, and that
center point of the screen was our
reference. So, we can just move that
over there like that, and bingo, 94.4.
But, you'll notice that the resolution
jumps 0.2. That's the best resolution
we've got at the moment. And of course,
you can single shot capture this too if
you have to. So, you can see how we're
only getting a 0.2 microsecond
resolution there when we shift that. So,
to increase that resolution, what we can
do is we can get it so that both of
these are on screen. If no, that's not
I'm going to have to go down to time
base like that. Okay? And then we can
single shot capture that. Okay? And then
if we center it like that where it's
zero there, and then we can just bring
this over, and instead of just measuring
it like that and get our point, you
know, be happy with our 0.2
microseconds, we can increase our time
base like that.
And go in there, and you'll see that now
it's finer. So, we've got 94.
So, what's that jump in at 0.08?
I think. Yeah, 0.08
microseconds there. So, we can actually
get just a finer resolution there. But,
you can see that we're kind of getting
towards like the sampling uh limit here
cuz we're only 10K points memory. So, we
got the extra little resolution, but you
know, it's it's good enough. But, if you
really want to increase your chances,
you can actually change your sample rate
here. Let's go in there, and let's go to
our full 10 meg of memory like that, and
we can now single shot capture that
again, and you can see that we've got
more data in there. It's more better,
huh? And we're now point 04
point Yeah, point 04. It's jumping in
resolution there. So, that's just a way
to get a slightly finer or greater
resolution measurement there like that.
And that's 94.32
microseconds. And we can take that
figure and we get like 33.9.
So, we can actually get a little bit
more equal bit more resolution out of it
there by single shot capturing expanding
it and then shifting the waveform over
and then choosing a reference point.
It's easy just to get the you know, the
center of the screen. And yeah, you can
get a bit better that way, but
but here you're saying, "Dave, those
four or five ways isn't enough. I need
another way to do it." Okay, there is
another way to do it. Once again, a very
old school stuff. Let's go in here and
we can go into XY mode and we can get
ourselves
a listen what's called a Lissajous
figure. Pronounce that three times
quickly. So, what is XY mode? Well, it's
a little bit deceiving because our
channels
channel one is actually also called the
X channel and channel two is called the
Y channel. And you might be able to set
that up you know, on your scope for
which channels it's using, but let's
just go with that. So, it's plotting the
voltage on channel one on the X axis and
the voltage on the Y axis is the voltage
on channel two. And for two sine waves
that are offset like this, we get an
ellipse. So, I'll demonstrate this. I'll
call my measurements back up here. So,
let's Sorry, I can't actually float that
measurement out. So, and I don't want to
get rid of the sine wave screen over
here. So, we're going to have to live
with that. So, let me adjust the phase
angle and you'll see that as I'm
adjusting it, it gets once if I go down
to a phase angle of zero Well, that is
zero. We get a straight line like that.
Both waveforms match perfectly like
that, so we get a straight angled line.
But, the more that we go out, and you
guessed it, if we go up to all the way
up to 90°
70, 80,
and 90°, we get a perfect circle there.
And as we increase at 100°, we go the
opposite direction. And if we go 180
right up to 180°,
and whoop whoop, there it is there.
Perfect straight line like that. And
then we can go beyond 180° of course,
and it's just going to go backwards like
that. Cool, huh? So, you can also
technically use this display to actually
measure your angle. Calculating the
phase angle from this Lissajous figure
is a little bit tricky, but we should be
able to in theory do it. So, if we call
up our cursors, at the moment our
cursors are only working on the time
display over here, but if we go in there
and we go into the settings, we can
actually set that to XY mode, and now
our cursors are available on our XY
display over here. So, I'll just get rid
of that waveform so that we get our
Lissajous figure full screen like this.
All right, so let me just move those
horizontal cursors out of there cuz we
don't need those. We're going to focus
on our vertical cursors. So, what we
want to do is move our cursor here until
the point where it intersects that Y
axis there at that point, and then the
other cursor we want to put at the
maximum amplitude
there of our
the ellipse there. So, oval circle,
whichever it happens to be. So, we can
calculate out our angle with voltages
here, and this is really cool. So, Um
the Y value here is 1.062.
So, 1.062
V
and then we divide that by the maximum
value up here, which is 2.046
V. That's the AY figure divided by 2.046
V
and that gives us a value of .51 and
then we want to do arc sine. So, it's
that sine -1 there on your calculator.
You might never have used it. But if we
use that, boom, that is our phaser. That
happens to be our phase angle. It's a
little bit off because our resolution's
not great,
but it's there. And then if I wind this
up to 90°,
okay, and it's perfect like that, then
the both values are the same, 2.046.
Like it intersects at 2.046 and the
maximum value is 2.046, which is you
divide those two figures, it's just one.
And then if you've got one and then you
do your arc sine like that. You've got
to be in degrees mode, of course. Bingo,
there's our 90° and we're we have a 90°
phase difference between these two. So,
it works. Magic. And for those
wondering, yes, I was just using XY mode
for funsies there. You can actually do
this on the regular
time display as well. When you've got
your waveform centered like this, you
just take your the channel that you want
to measure there. So, the Y cursor there
is 1.055
V. You divide that by the maximum value
up there, which is BY, which is 2.102
equals that. Shift
arc sine and bingo, 30.12°.
Not quite the 33°, but you know, good
enough for Australia. And because like
we don't have the actual
the measurement resolution there, I'll
leave it up to you experiment at home
how you can get better resolution on
that. But cool, huh? You can get arc
sign of voltage levels to actually
measure your phase angle. Neat. So,
there you have it. There's just like
half a dozen different ways to use your
oscilloscope to measure phase between
two waveforms. So, thank you very much
for that question. Very interesting. If
you want to send me questions, you can
always tag me on X or  Twitter,
depends what you want to call it.
Anyway, if you like that video, please
give it a big thumbs up and as always
discuss down below. And if you want to
get yourself some top quality multimeter
merch, head on over to evblog.store
down below and that's the best way to
support the channel as well as, you
know, liking, subscribing. Oh, almost at
a million subscribers. Maybe might get
this year in there this year. Maybe. I
don't know.
Catch you next time.
>> [music]